A Guide to the Alexander Jackson Davis Architectural Drawings, 1859-1870
Virginia Military Institute Archives
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
Alexander Jackson Davis Architectural Drawings 1859-1870
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
mss 00276
The collection consists of 27 items.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Alternative Form
The Alexander Jackson Davis Drawings can be viewed online on the VMI Archives website at: http://www.vmi.edu/archives/manuscripts/ms276.html
Biographical/Historical Information
Alexander Jackson Davis (1803-1892), a notable 19th century American architect, designed the Virginia Military Institute Barracks, professors' residences and other Institute buildings during the 1850's-1860's. Born in New York, Davis studied at the American Academy of Fine Arts and the National Academy of Design. He helped to popularize the Greek Revival, Gothic Revival, and Italianate styles, and his many important projects included private residences as well as public buildings. Davis has long been recognized by historians as the most significant American practitioner of the "secular gothic," and VMI was the first American college planned entirely in the Gothic Revival style. This style incorporates towers, turrets, and other design elements first used in medieval castles and cathedrals. The VMI Barracks was designated a National Historic Landmark in 1966, and the VMI Post was named a National Historic District in 1974.
Davis's association with VMI came about as a result of his design work for Philip St. George Cocke, a wealthy Virginia planter and member of the VMI Board of Visitors. Cocke, an impassioned advocate of the Gothic style, employed Davis to design "Belmead" the Cocke residence in Powhatan County, Virginia. Cocke became Davis's patron in the state, and when VMI began its building program in the late 1840's, it turned to Davis to create a comprehensive plan for the Institute. During the period 1850-1861, a significant portion of the Barracks, a Porter's Lodge, Mess Hall, the Superintendent's residence, and several faculty residences were constructed using Davis's designs. Davis's dream of completing the Barracks quadrangle was interrupted by the Civil War and VMI's post-war financial problems, and his work for the Institute ended in the 1870's. It was not until the early 20th century that his vision for the Parade Ground facade of Barracks was realized, based on a Davis-inspired design by another noted architect, Bertram Goodhue.
Scope and Content Information
The Alexander Jackson Davis collection consists of 27 architectural drawings executed for the Virginia Military Institute (Lexington, Virginia) between 1859 and 1870. Included are designs for the VMI Barracks, the Superintendent's residence, and faculty residences. The bulk of the drawings are ink and wash plans.
Contents List
- Superintendent's Residence, Virginia Military Institute, 1860, 9 items
  - "Executive Mansion, Va. Military Inst., Lexington, Va. 1860." Front Elevation., Ink & wash drawing, 18 3/4 x 13 1/2 inches.
  - "Plan No. 2, Principal Floor, adopted for the Executive Mansion, Va. Military Institute, Lexington, Va. 1860.", Ink & wash drawing, 18 3/4 x 12 inches.
  - "Dwelling House and Offices for the Superintendent at Va. Milit. Institute. Oct 1859. A. J. Davis, Archit." Plan & front elevation., Ink & wash drawing, 16 1/2 x 10 1/2 inches.
  - Unexecuted first floor plan, front and rear elevations; detail of parlor window., Ink & wash plan and detail, 18 3/4 x 12 inches.
  - First floor plan, drawing "A.", Ink & wash drawing, 18 3/4 x 12 inches.
  - First floor plan, drawing "B." Front & back elevations., Ink & wash drawing, 18 3/4 x 12 inches.
  - Front Elevation, pencil, Ink & wash drawing, 18 1/2 x 12 inches.
  - Second Floor plan; section; front elevation., Ink & wash plan; section and elevation in pencil; 18 1/2 x 12 inches.
  - "Plan No. 3. Chamber Floor, Adopted for the Executive Mansion, VMI, 1860.", Ink & wash plan; ink section; 18 1/2 x 12 inches.
- Faculty Residences, VMI Parade Ground, 1850's, 8 items
  - Plan and elevation, "River Front.", Ink & wash drawing, 24 x 19 inches.
  - "First Study, A, for Professor's house, Va. Mil. Inst.", Ink & wash drawing, 14 x 17 inches
  - Elevation (C4) & Plan (C1), Ink & wash drawing, rendered elevation, 11 x 14 inches
  - Elevation, "Entrance front 5A;" & Plan, "Second story No. 3 - A2.", Ink & wash drawing with pencil, 14 x 17 inches
  - Elevation (B4) and "Plan of Second story 3" (B3)., Ink & wash drawing, 14 x 17 inches
  - Elevation (B5) and Plan (B2). "First A and second study B for the V.M.I; principal floor enlarged.", Ink & wash drawing, 14 x 17 inches
  - Elevation (B6), "West End," & Plan (B1), "Basement No. 1.", Ink & wash drawing, 14 x 17 inches
  - Elevation (C5) and Plan (C2), "Upper Story.", Ink & wash drawing, rendered elevation, 11 x 14 inches
- Barracks, 1870, 10 items
  These post-Civil War designs for "Claytor Hall" -- intended to complete the Barracks project begun in the 1850s -- were never executed. VMI was struggling to recover from the destruction of Institute buildings by Union General David Hunter, and would not be able to continue with Davis's ambitious design. The parade ground facade of Barracks, as originally envisioned by Davis, was completed in the early 20th century.
  - "Claytor Hall - Va. Milit. Inst. Gen. Fr. H. Smith Supn'dt - Lexington, Virginia. - A. J. Davis, Arc't.", Ink & wash drawing, mounted; 13 1/2 x 9 1/4 inches.
  - "Claytor Hall, No. 5. Cross section; and Center, south front. 1870.", Ink & wash drawing, mounted; 13 1/2 x 9 1/4 inches.
  - Plan, "Barracks of the Virginia Military Institute;" with overlay, "Plan on the Floor of Museums, No. 3.", Ink & wash drawing; plan 23 1/2 x 19 1/2; overlay 11 x 5 inches.
  - Detail working drawing of octagonal auditorium., Ink & wash drawing, 23 1/2 x 18 inches
  - "Study for No. 3, Memorial Chapel.", Ink & wash drawing, 11 x 9 inches
  - "Basement No. 1. By A. J. Davis architect, 1870.", Ink & wash drawing, 35 x 12 inches
  - "No. 2, Principal or Entrance Floor.", Ink & wash plan with architect's notes, 35 x 12 inches
  - "No. 3 Chapel and Museum Floor.", Ink & wash plan with architect's notes, 35 x 12 inches
  - "Attic and Ceilings, Va. Mil. Inst., No. 4.", Ink plan, stairway overlay, 35 x 10 inches
  - "No. 5, Long Section, Claytor Hall.", Ink & wash drawing, 35 x 12 inches